Guide to the Edgar Tristram Thompson papers, 1915 - 1985 UA.29.02.0025
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Edgar Tristram Thompson papers
1915 - 1985
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Thompson, Edgar Tristram, 1900-
UA.29.02.0025
4.5 Linear Feet
Edgar Tristram Thompson taught Sociology at Duke University from 1937 until his retirement in 1970. The papers include correspondence with Herbert Blumer, Charles Ellwood, Eric Hoffer, Everett Hughes, and Howard Jensen; teaching materials from undergraduate and graduate courses in race relations, religion, and social anthropology; lecture notes from Thompson's mentor and sociology instructor Robert E. Park; research on plantations in Hawaii and in Africa as the Hugh le May Fellow at Rhodes University; development and operations of a Black Studies program and Center for Southern Studies at Duke University; short papers discussing race relations at Duke University and racial identity; autobiographical histories of Thompson's students; manuscripts for many books on race relations; records of participation in Alpha Kappa Delta and American Sociological Association conferences; a campus-wide graffiti survey; and addresses to the Mayor's Committee on Interracial Affairs of Durham. English.
3,000 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Edgar Tristram Thompson papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1963-1990.
Biographical Note
Edgar Tristram Thompson received his instruction in sociology and education from the University of South Carolina and the University of Chicago. Thompson was a Professor of Sociology at Duke University from 1935 to 1970 and founder and chair of the Center for Southern Studies. He conducted plantation research in South Africa from 1965-1968 as a Hugh Le May Fellow at Rhodes University. Thompson served as President of the Southern Sociological Society in 1961 and was a participant in many conferences on race relations. He was an expert on the the anthropology of race and plantation society in the South; he also did extensive research on community structures. His main works were Race Relations and the Race Problem; a Definition and an Analysis (1939), Race and Region (1949), Race: Individual and Collective Behavior (1958) and The Plantation: An International Bibliography (1983).
Collection Overview
The material in this collection addresses American race relations and scholarly treatment of race from about 1940 to 1970. The bulk of the records date from 1920 to 1970. Included are manuscripts of papers by Thompson, his thesis, a bound volume of selected writings, personal and professional correspondence, printed matter, research notes, proofs, departmental budgets and other materials relating to the study and teaching of sociology. Primary sources include handwritten autobiographical histories written by African American students and surveys from a nationwide graffiti project. Major subjects in the manuscripts include race relations in the United States and in other countries, the South, religion in the South, international plantation systems, and sociological anthropology. There is also a small amount of material on the sociology of language. Also included are histories of the Department of Sociology, articles presented in symposia and conferences by Thompson, correspondence concerning the development, establishment, and operations of the Duke Center for Southern Studies (1965 to 1969) and the formation of a Black Studies program (1969). There are also papers from the Mayor's Committee on Interracial Affairs of Durham from 1945. Other materials include newspaper articles which address problems and violence in race relations and publicity of race relations events at Duke.
In addition to scholarly topics in sociology, this collection introduces perspectives on race relations at Duke University during the politically active 1960s and 1970s. There are a number of articles about Duke-sponsored race relations learning activities. Thompson was a strong advocate of learning about personal racial heritage and understanding social structures and events though that frame. He tried for many years, without success, to gain the Ford Foundation's sponsorship of race relations conferences and seminars; this topic received much attention from scholars in sociology. Correspondents include contemporary sociologists Herbert Blumer, Charles Ellwood, Eric Hoffer, Everett Hughes, and Howard Jensen. Thompson's greatest influence was Robert E. Park, a former instructor who was also an expert on race relations theory and plantation systems.
The Edgar T. Thompson papers were originally unorganized. Folders contained many types of documents covering a variety of topics and were loosely grouped by date according to year of accession of the material. The folders have since been further grouped into several series, and further by date within each series, where applicable. Many items in this collection are undated. A list of Thompson's writing can be found at the front of the bound volume The Papers of Dr. Edgar T. Thompson.
Plantation life -- Southern States; Graffiti -- North Carolina; Plantations -- Hawaii; Plantations -- Africa; African Americans -- Study and teaching; African Americans -- Race identity; Ethnology -- Study and teaching; Durham (N.C.) -- Race relations; Southern States -- Race relations; African Americans -- Autobiography; Southern States -- Social conditions; Race relations -- Study and teaching; Religion -- Study and teaching; Slavery -- United States; Ellwood, Charles A. (Charles Abram), 1873-1946; Hoffer, Eric; Hughes, Everett Cherrington, 1897-; Jensen, Howard Eikenberry, 1889-1970; Park, Robert Ezra, 1864-1944; Rhodes University; Thompson, Edgar Tristram, 1900-; Thompson, Edgar Tristram, 1900-; Alpha Kappa Delta; American Sociological Association; Blumer, Herbert, 1900-1987; Duke University -- Faculty; Duke University -- Students; Duke University. Center for Southern Studies in the Social Sciences and the Humanities; Duke University. Department of Sociology
- Correspondence, 1934-1981.
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes personal and professional correspondence from Herbert Blumer, Charles Ellwood, Eric Hoffer, Everett Hughes, and Howard Jensen about curriculum ideas, race relations, activities among colleagues, politics, and comments on papers and presentations.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged by date.
  - 1934-1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1969-1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Lectures, 1951-1952, undated
  Includes course outlines and reading lists from undergraduate and graduate courses taught by Thompson as Professor of Sociology at Duke University and Northwestern University. The course subjects cover race relations, physical anthropology, racial identity in the United States, and culture. The Readings in Introductory Sociology folders contain short summaries and commentaries of assigned readings for an entire course section.
  Arranged by course subject.
  - Northwestern University, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Duke University, Readings in Introductory Sociology (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Duke University, Lectures in Race and Culture (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Duke University, Course syllabi and reading lists (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Student Papers, 1951-1952, undated
  Includes papers written by undergraduate and graduate students of Thompson. Of particular interest are the Negro Life Histories, where Thompson asked students to write autobiographically about their personal experiences with race.
  - 1962-1969 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Negro Life Histories (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
- Programs of Study, 1930-1970.
  Includes extensive documentation of years of effort by Thompson and his colleagues to bring a race relations conference to Duke University.
  Arranged by program.
  - Center for Southern Studies, 1930-1966 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Center for Southern Studies, 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Center for Southern Studies, Budget, 1930-1966 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Center for Southern Studies, Publicity, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Afro-American Program, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Research, 1940-1981.
  Includes field notes, research assignments and assorted correspondence relating to scholarly study of race relations. Thompson followed the work of Robert E. Park while studying intermarriage, plantations, and race relations in Hawaii. Thompson was the Hugh Le May Fellow at Rhodes University in Rhodesia, Africa where he studied plantations and race relations. He later returned to study apartheid and social class in Africa during the summer of 1966. Thompson also conducted local research for a national survey of graffiti at universities around the United States and followed local developments and trends in racial composition of Durham, NC.
  Arranged by research topic.
  - Africa (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Graffiti (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
  - Hawaii (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
  - Intermarriage (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Literature (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Negro Population of Durham (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Plantations (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Notes (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Conferences, 1966-1969.
  Included are conference notes, programs, and collected conference papers of events where Thompson was a speaker or organizer. Thompson participated in conferences and symposia of Alpha Kappa Delta and the American Sociological Association on religion, race relations, and race in the South. The Proposals folder includes extensive documentation of years of effort by Thompson and his colleagues to bring a race relations conference to Duke University.
  Arranged by topic of conference.
  - The Changing South, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
  - American Sociological Association, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - The Bible Belt in Continuity and Change, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - LQC Lamar Society, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Religion in the Solid South, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Proposals, 1963-1969 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Miscellaneous [conferences] (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Writings, 1932-1985.
  Includes drafts of Race Relations and the Race Problem; a Definition and an Analysis (1939), Race and Region (1949), Race: Individual and Collective Behavior (1958) and The Plantation: An International Bibliography (1983) and related correspondence. Also includes short published and unpublished papers, a bound volume of collected papers, and Thompson's dissertation, The Plantation (1932).
  Arranged alphabetically by paper title or subject.
  - Bibliography on Race Relations (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Book Reviews (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Collecting (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - The Concept of Race (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Decency and the Good Old Boy Syndrome (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Dictionary of American History (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Ecology of Race Relations (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Language and Race Relations (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - The Negro (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Peoples (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Plantations as a Social System (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - The Plantation and its Legacy (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - The Plantation in the Pacific Area (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Race Classification (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Race Region (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Race Relations Reader (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Race Relations Reader, Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Regional Varieties of Race Relations (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Short Works (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Sociology at Duke University (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - US News and World Report (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - The Papers of Dr. Edgar T. Thompson (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - The Plantation (Box 3, Folder 59)
- Robert E. Park materials, 1920-1976.
  Includes correspondence, lecture notes, reading lists, and general short writings by Robert E. Park, a professor of Sociology at the University of Chicago during the 1930s. Also includes correspondence and drafts related to Park's biography, written by Winifred Raushenbush and edited by Thompson and Everett Hughes.
  - Biography, 1967-1976 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Lectures, 1920-1934, undated (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Miscellaneous [Park materials], 1917, undated (Box 3, Folder 62)
- Personal Materials, 1930-1977.
  Includes speeches made by Thompson, notes from Mayor's Committee (Durham, North Carolina) meetings, Kiwanis membership honors, a biographical sketch, and a family genealogy.
  - Speeches, 1930-1958, undated (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Mayor's Committee on Interracial Affairs of Durham (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Kiwanis (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Thompson family genealogy (Box 3, Folder 66)